<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true account of a letter sent from Vienna, August the 23rd 1683 declaring the rasing the seige and the total overthrow of all the Turkish army / sent in a letter from an eminent English officer under the Duke of Lorraine, to his father at White-Hall.</title>
            <author>W. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13174456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13174456</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98341</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98341)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 445:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true account of a letter sent from Vienna, August the 23rd 1683 declaring the rasing the seige and the total overthrow of all the Turkish army / sent in a letter from an eminent English officer under the Duke of Lorraine, to his father at White-Hall.</title>
                  <author>W. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Geogre [sic] Croom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: W. B.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Vienna (Austria) --  History --  Siege, 1683 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98341:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98341:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TRUE ACCOUNT OF A LETTER SENT FROM VIENNA <date>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> the 23d 1683.</date>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Declaring the raſing the SEIGE and the Total Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, ſent in a Letter from an Eminent <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officer under the Duke of <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> to his Father at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I am in duty bound to give you Account of my being, as you are the Perſon from whom I derive it, ſo I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelf obliged (next after God, from whoſe infinite Mercies I do from the bottom of my Heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to receive my preſervation and well-being) to let you, and my Friends in <hi>England</hi> underſtand, as well as of my ſelf, the preſervation of a great part of Chriſtendom, from the fury, rage and threatning Ruine, of that implacable and univerſal Enemy the <hi>Turk,</hi> who under the Command of the Grand <hi>Viſier,</hi> with a very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Army, conſiſting of near an Hundred and Fifty Thouſand men, had a very conſiderable time Beſeiged the Imperial City of <hi>Vienna;</hi> for the relief of which the Emperour had confederated all the Friends and Allyes he could in all the adjacent Territories, among which indeed I muſt ſay the chiefeſt was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> whoſe Conduct and Valour had been ſufficiently proved againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> by the ſeveral conſiderable overthrows he hath given them, in Defence of that ſmall Kingdom of <hi>Poland,</hi> and together with him the Dukes of <hi>Bavaria, Saxany,</hi> and others of the Princes; of the Empire had joyned as they were able to bring up their Forces ſo that in effect, with the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> who Commanded as General all the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial ſtanding Forces, they had compacted a prety conſiderable Body with which it was adviſed they might, with the bleſſing of God, relieve this miſerably diſtreſſed City. And thus we marched on to try what could be done, but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> deſired Firſt, that he might be a little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the poſture of the Enemy, and to that purpoſe drew out a conſiderable party of Horſe, and marched on till he came within view of their Leaguer, the Army, eſpecially of Horſe, following after with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and Expedition, ſo that although the <hi>Turk,</hi> had by his Scout and Spies Intelligence, that there was a powerful Army approaching him, yet he drew leiſurely out of his Trenches, not dreading, any great Oppoſition, eſpecially becauſe he was informed of a ſtrong body of the <hi>Bours</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:98341:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>Country, who had gathered to an Head not far from him, Now indeed theſe poor people having been ſo long oppreſſed, and driven from their Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by the <hi>Turks,</hi> ever ſince they came before <hi>Vienna,</hi> hearing of the Conjunction of ſo many good Chriſtian Princes, drawing towards <hi>Vienna</hi> to relieve it, thought it was now time, not to hide themſelves any longer in Holes, and therefore addreſſing themſelves to ſome old Commanders, who were in an equal condition with themſelves, they marched on a little too haſtily towards the Enemy, who ſuppoſing theſe the greateſt Force com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him, ſent preſently a party to diſſolve them, which fell with ſuch Violence upon theſe poor Men, but half armed, and at the Firſt worſted them, and as is ſuppoſed deſtroyed above 1500 on the place; but juſt at the ſame Inſtant the King of <hi>Poland</hi> aſſiſted by the Emperour himſelf and the others, with a full Body of reſolute Horſe, fell violently upon the <hi>Turks</hi> Army, who by this time had clearly left their Trenches, and fell upon them with that Conduct, valour and reſolution, eſpecially upon the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> that they were ſoon diſordered, and in a ſhort time became a Prey to the Swo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, by which means the <hi>Turks</hi> main Strength and relyance was quite diſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, and all the reſt, who were very numerous, being now bravely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted on all hands, (for by this time the <hi>Bours,</hi> who had before ſuffered, ſome little diſcomfeiture, by the conduct and advice of their Leaders had rallyed and made conſiderable Oppoſition) ſubmitted to a General defeat. Tho I mention onely the conduct of that Heroick King of <hi>Poland,</hi> whoſe Honour can never be enough applauded, yet his Imperial Majeſty was in perſon an Actor in this memorable Battle, as alſo ſeveral Princes of the Empire, whoſe Catalogue would ſwell my Letter to an unpleaſing length. It is not computed to be a leſs Number of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſlain than 90 or 100000, amongſt which is the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> himſelf, and ſo many of the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> that 'tis beleived there will hardly eſcape Twenty of them to carry the News to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to comfort the Grand <hi>Signiour,</hi> the purſuit is ſo violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Proſecuted, and all the paſſages ſo warily Guarded. I cannot deſcend at preſent to any further particulars, taking advantage of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſenger, whoſe haſt is ſuch that I cannot more nicely inform my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being in a great Hurry, as moſt are at preſent here, but within few days you ſhall have a further Satisfaction from,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honored Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt obedient Son <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I Have been ſo intent in relating the Proceedings of the Armies, that I had quite omitted the condition in which we found <hi>Vienna,</hi> who th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently couragious, yet was in very great diſtreſs. The laſt Storm the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nemy made upon them was forced on with ſuch Violence, that the account the people of the City gave of it, ſeems, in their own words very proper as they render it, that they came upon them like Mountains of Men, as they appeared, more then Armies, for the <hi>Turk</hi> forced his men on ſo faſt, that they run over one another and thoſe that were ſlain or beaten down, were but Footſteps and degrees of advantage, to mount the ſucceſſive Troop to that height, that they could in a manner overlook the City-Walls, and in that manner came pouring on with ſuch a deſperation, it was very hard to withſtand them. Yet by the Bleſſing of God, and the weak endeavors of the beſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, they were repelled with a very great loſs to the <hi>Turks,</hi> and 'tis thought near 5000 of the Beſeiged. Which cauſed the Governour to ſend to the General, that he could not poſſibly withſtand ſuch another Aſſault, which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence haſtened our Army to the relief of it, as you have in this L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ter.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Geogre Croom</hi> at the <hi>Blew Ball</hi> in <hi>Tham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſtreet</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynards Caſtle.</hi> 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98341:2"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
